Finding Aid for Lawrence Llewellyn Farrell Papers, 1935-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lawrence Llewellyn Farrell Papers 1935-1971
Farrell, Lawrence Llewellyn, 1903-1971.
851301 Aa 2; UAm
Works Projects Administration district manager, official in the Office of Price Administration and executive secretary to Governor G. Mennen Williams. Materials concerning Michigan Democratic politics, particularly the elections of 1948 and 1952, his work for the W.P.A. and O.P.A. and his with the Michigan Children's Aid Society.
3.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Farrell (donor no. 5171 ) and came to the library in 1971.
The collection is open to research.
Lawrence L. Farrell was born in Hardwood in Dickinson County, Michigan. He graduated from the University of Michigan in 1926, then went to work for the National Cash Register Co. In 1933, he joined the State Highway Department office in Escanaba as engineering assistant. From 1935 to 1937, Farrell was an employment supervisor for the Works Progress Administration also in Escanaba. In 1937, he returned to the Highway Department as supervisor of the maintenance division of the Upper Peninsula. In 1940, he returned to the WPA as district manager in the Marquette office. In 1943, he was named district OPA director for the Upper Peninsula, later moving to Saginaw to head that OPA district. He became state director in 1946 where G. Mennen Williams was his deputy. In 1948, Governor-elect William selected Farrell to be his executive secretary where he served until 1959. During the campaign, Farrell served as Williams' out-state campaign manager. After leaving the Williams administration, he became administrator of the state retirement system. He was also on the board of the Michigan Children's Aid Society, Ingham County Branch. He died July 27, 1971.
The Farrell collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence, Political Papers, Works Projects Administration, Office of Price Administration, and Other Papers.
Subjects:
Democratic Party (Mich.); Elections--Michigan--1948.; Elections--Michigan--1952.; Michigan Children's Aid Society.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; United States. Office of Price Administration.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1953.; United States--Politics and government--1953-1961.; United States. Work Projects Administration.; Governors--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Democratic Party (Mich.); Ford, John, 1894-1973.; Gladstone (Mich.); Golf.; Harbors.; Offices--Michigan--Escanaba.; Political elections.; Roads--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Ships--Great Lakes.; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.; United States. Work Projects Administration.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Contributors:
Bennett, John B. (John Bonifas), 1905-1964.; Bradley, Frederick Van Ness, 1898-1947.; Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Hook, Frank Eugene, 1893-1982.; Staebler, Neil, 1905-2000; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1935-1958, 30 folders (Box 1)
- Political papers
  - Undated 1936-1950, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1951-1958, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Directory of Democratic Party workers 1940 (Box 2)
  - Election recount papers 1952, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Works Projects Administration 1935-1937, 1940-1943
  - LLF personnel file (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Travel vouchers, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Office of Price Administration 1943-1947
  - Papers undated, 1943-1946, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Move of the district office to Escanaba 1943 (Box 2)
  - Wayne County claim 1943-1946 (Box 2)
  - LLF personnel file 1943-1947 (Box 2)
  - Published material; scrapbook of "memory bonds" from Detroit District Office to LLF (Box 3)
  - Radio talks for the O.P.A. 1946, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Travel vouchers 1943-1947, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1943 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1943-1945 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1945 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1946-1947 (Box 3)
- Other Papers
  - Michigan Children's Aid Society, Ingham County Branch 1966-1971, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Mackinac Bridge miscellanea 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and other papers, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    - WPA Projects (Box 4)
    - WPA officials and functions (Box 4)
    - G. Mennen Williams and the Williams administration (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous: include John Ford and Murray D. Van Wagoner; Upper Peninsula campaign headquarters 1940 and photo of Farrell with Adlai Stevenson (Box 4)
  - Metal artifact: image of a laughing donkey with the inscription "The Will of a Free People: 46 to 2" circa 1940 (Box 4)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Bennett, John B. (John Bonifas), 1905-1964
1944
Bradley, Frederick Van Ness, 1898-1947.
1944-1946
Brown, Prentiss Marsh, 1889-1973.
1941-1943
Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976
October 10, 1950, February 28, 1952
Hook, Frank Eugene, 1893-1982.
November 14, 1944, 1945, 1946
Staebler, Neil, 1905-
November 10, 1949, May 15, 1950, December 29, 1950, May 16, 1951, 1952, September 30, 1955
Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-
1937, 1938, 1940
Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-
1947, 1948, January 2, 1950, March 22, 1952, March 31, 1952